Kicking off our talks, we have the wonderful
Dana Lawson who is the CTO of Netlify and of course Netlify for many, many years
have been have been building wonderful software for a world that is agent less.
And now we have agents.
So Dana is going to tell us how we adapt for that.
So please welcome on stage Dana Lawson.
Have a great session.
Oh man.
How do y'all. Good morning.
I'm a little jet
lagged and a little caffeinated, so hopefully I don't talk to darn fast.
But I'll tell you what.
Coming into the city yesterday, I was I became an Arsenal fan.
Y'all are crazy.
I was like, what the hell is going on here?
Somebody should have warned me, but y'all sure do you know how to party?
So I was down, but I didn't clown last night.
I had had to be serious for this.
All right, so as you heard, I'm Dana Lawson, CTO of Netlify.
Netlify is, as we all are, a web application platform.
We help anybody build, deploy and create experiences.
And now in an agent world, guess what?
Anybody can do it.
And so our world is changing so rapidly that this talk
might be out of date, but maybe not.
Depends on how far you are in your journey.
So let's get going. So
before we get into the
architecture, I need to say something that might feel uncomfortable.
How many of you here identify as a developer?
Oh man, we ain't precious no more, y'all.
The builder persona has changed.
The person our platforms were built for are no longer just developers.
We're still builders, don't get me wrong, but we're not the only ones.
Now, with agents, anybody can participate.
In fact, the IDC predicts that more than 500
million new applications will be built by 2028.
And in fact, I create one a day.
So I'm a I'm a part of that damn problem more than the previous 40 years combined.
Think about it for a minute now,
40 years have been compressed into three, just like this room.
That's not because the number of engineers is expanding.
It's because agents have turned intent into a programming language.
In fact, the strongest programming language that will happen now
and into the future is guess what, English.
So I hope you go and study that in school.
Kids, if you're watching you better, you better learn how to talk to somebody.
Claude.
Code, Cursor.
Bolt, Lovable, Netlify.
These tools let anyone with an idea create working software through conversations.
No longer is it just developers.
It's therapists, teachers, small business owners, students,
people in line at the store building experiences on their phone.
Thank you.
Lovable and becoming software
creators at Netlify, we build for all of these builders.
And here's the thing.
When we designed our platform to work better for agents
serving these new builders, it got better for developers too.
And that's the paradox.
So let me tell you a little story.
Let me introduce you to my best friend, my home girl, Toria.
This is her. She is a licensed massage therapist.
She's a vibrant drummer, a delightful, authentic, woo woo Burning Man hippie.
So I can't even believe she hangs out with an AI overlord.
But she does.
And she just radiates incredible energy.
She has a dream.
She came to me and she said, girl, I want to build
an all inclusive experience, not just a website.
I ain't going on to Wix.
I want to build an app for my Barbados massage retreat, where I can build
community and I can take payments and I can can deliver content.
These aren't just static website dreams.
These are full blown application dreams.
She doesn't write the code.
She really just writes intentions.
And she decided she was going to build this website.
So she went on to her favorite chat application, ChatGPT,
and described her vision and she started building.
She prompted an agent to build the website, but every assumption
we have baked in to the tooling turned out to be a human assumption.
As we originally had built Netlify,
it was for front end developers, and now we realized with agents
we were lowering that gatekeeping in that barrier.
First it was about git.
She had no idea what git was.
I worked at GitHub. Some other GitHub people are here.
I was like, man, you don't need to know what git is.
Trust me on this. But she was stuck.
This is the reality for millions of new builders right now.
Agents still speak fluent developer, but the humans they're serving don't.
They don't know.
They don't know posts.
They don't know anything.
First, this was.
She had no idea what she's doing.
The tools assumed
a level of technical literacy that most of the world just does not have.
And this is the thing that really surprises Netlify.
As we were redesigning for agents, fixing this for Toria
also fixed it for our experienced developers
that have to write with spec, intent, context, all the things that Guy said
with the new software delivery lifecycle, those are the things that we have
to just make work out of the box, because the new builder has no idea.
When we made the agent's error messages clear and structured
the build output for machine, and removed unnecessary friction.
Our developers also benefited from this.
Every human assumption we remove made the platform better for everyone.
This is the gap of what we call agent experience.
So as I said, she called me.
I was like, girl, you don't need to worry about git.
You don't have to worry about deploy. You need to just go.
You just need to go prompt your vision into the world.
And I got you.
But this got me thinking about what this means.
After years, I've been a software developer.
Builder QA.
I've done it all, man. I've been doing this since the 90s.
Maybe decades of building guardrails to prevent humans from breaking production.
We're now removing those guardrails and saying, hey, come play with us.
Come, come create, go build the next experiences for the world. Why?
Because the interfaces have changed.
The agent now handles git.
It handles deployment, it handles DNS.
The builder focuses on the vision.
And and this is really what agent experience in practice looks like.
Agents have full access to our platform primitives.
They deploy configure iterate so the human never touches anything.
It's pretty scary right.
So under the hood
you're going to have all the things that you need to make it frictionless
so that builders in this new breed of developers can get those ideas out.
AX captures the humanity in this story.
It removes that technical friction.
So again, people like Toria or anybody else with a good idea
that wants to change humanity for the better, they can now do it.
But here's the key insight.
Again, we didn't just make this as a separate dumbed down platform.
If you go on to Netlify
is still as powerful as it was ten years ago as it is today.
But we had to think about how
that intersection of developers and builders are coming together.
So what do we do?
We just built a better platform for everyone.
The same structure signals that help that agent deploy to a site.
Also helped our engineers to bug and build faster build systems, understand where
we have errors under the hood, really help us create that magical experience.
And so what we learned was designing for agents,
actually was designing for humans all along.
And so this shift brings me to my core thesis.
You've all heard user experience we heard in 2012.
Jeremiah at Spotify coined developer experience in my boss Matt Billman
last year said, you know what the new paradigm is?
AX, DX, and UX are collapsing into a single discipline.
And here's why.
Again, that builder persona is no longer you.
The agents are doing the heavy lifting.
So when you're thinking about how that end user interacts, it's also an agent.
When you're thinking about how that developer
goes and programs on your platform.
It's not a developer, it's an agent.
But on the other end is a human that just speaks plain English
and expects it to just work.
And again, agent experience isn't about making machines happy.
It's about removing that friction every step of the way
so that you can get from idea into reality in a few simple prompts.
Now, I know that's again scary for all of us as software developers, but
haven't we always just built so that we can explore, collaborate,
and share our ideas?
And some of us actually change humanity?
I hope for the better.
Deploy so structured errors and agents can parse.
Engineers can stand them faster to
and then deploy previews that give agents clear pass fail signals.
These all give us human clarity, and a lot of this stuff is often skated.
We don't need the end user to think about it anymore.
And now the end user is anybody.
Because we are building a development platform, we have to just make it work.
So as you heard in Guy's talk, really Agent Experience is thinking
about all that new system content and intent in the SDLC.
It is the practice of designing where humans and agents collaborate seamlessly.
And it isn't just about making API API calls agent friendly.
You really do have to rethink the entire stack along the way from how
we express the intent to how systems communicate and so that we can trust.
So let's look at the landscape.
You already heard a little bit from Guy of what's changing.
And like I said,
some of this is probably out of date as I open my mouth in just two years.
That's right.
And only two years
we've seen an explosion of these AI powered development tools or harnesses.
I mean, call them what you will.
I'm sure the name is going to change many, many times.
I was sitting here thinking, man, Netlify is a harness on a harness on a harness.
That's so damn meta. How many harnesses do you need?
So I hope somebody comes out with the second hard
human problem, which is naming things.
Claude Code from Anthropic is an agent
CLI that writes, tests, and commits. Cursor and Windsurf AI
pair program with you. v0,
Netlify, Bolt
from StackBlitz, Lovable, all turn natural language into applications.
GitHub Copilot now has agent modes that autonomously works on
issues and submits PRs — the idea of a software factory.
It's been instilled for years.
This is not a new concept that we're determining here,
but now with agents, we can actually go and implement
those software factories to go and just run.
All of these again, share a common pattern intent
as input working software is output.
But there's the thing they all need infrastructure that understands
the patterns, the deploy target targets, the C pipelines, the edge networks.
They all have to be designed for agents.
And that's what we've been building at Netlify.
So what actually is changing?
Again, you've heard it.
It's gone from the SDLC.
The big shift is we're moving from
to intent.
Specs still matter.
And when you have large scale technical
platforms like myself, believe me, you're still using specs.
But for your average user, because I hate to break it to you,
the internet is just a bunch of apps and websites.
It's not that hard if you're a tech company.
It's hard if you're an end user that's building an experience.
Not that hard anymore.
Traditional development workflows typically would begin
with a PRD that passes to a ticket or a linear ticket.
Spec docs written for humans AI native workflows
begin with prompts, problem descriptions, sketches, and references.
The input is the intent.
I want a wellness retreat with booking, not a 50 page requirement doc.
This is where we have to think about how can we take that intent in those ideas
and turn them into reality by creating the software factories beneath them?
And at Netlify, we've been dog food.
In this we have a tool called Agent Runners.
An agent now or a harness takes the intent, generates the code.
The output moves immediately into real engineering workflows.
Preview deploys automated tests, production pipelines.
What used to take millions of minutes
now takes seconds, which is pretty darn incredible.
And so the second shift that we're seeing in the software
development lifecycle, with the rise of agent coding and the builder persona
becoming the every person is, we're moving from those sequential handoffs to
shared creation pipelines.
Now for Netlify,
yes, we have a sophisticated software development team and all people do
participate.
And historically, it was that relay relay race
that we all knew: PMs write the specs
hands to design, design creates the mockups, hands it to engineering.
Engineering builds it.
If you have QA, probably not. It's just a bot.
It validates it and it hands it to the DevOps
for deployment because nobody trusts anybody to go and hit that button.
But let me tell you, that takes weeks.
And some crazy billionaire bald tech overlords
said there ain't no doors you can't walk through.
You can't walk the other way back through.
So having that mindset of shipping
rapidly is now more so a reality than ever before.
So now instead of having these handoffs, this collaborative
product teams are generating working prototypes with agents.
Designers are redefining the experience directly in code.
They're not participating outside the lifecycle.
Engineers are now spending their time validating the architecture, and again,
spending time writing those precious guardrails
that didn't exist the way they need to exist now,
whether it's contact specs, recipes, etc.
we'll call it skills for ease of use as well.
Agents handled the testing and deployment and now everybody participates.
The cycle time compresses again from weeks to hours.
Third, what was the other change that we
this is the software factory layer that you heard in the previous talk.
Third, we move from passive CI pipelines to development loops.
That is one thing that I always brought to developers was like, hey,
you don't have to go and create your own CI/CD.
You can come to Netlify, we'll set it up and we'll get it configured for you.
But that has gone even crazier now with autonomous development loops.
Agents don't just write the code, they're participating
in the entire infrastructure lifecycle.
They're generating the test,
detecting fall failing previews, analyzing build logs, proposing fixes.
And so CI/CD just becomes a continuous feedback loop.
And some of you may not be at that level of sophistication, but
this is where you need to start thinking about how you're reinventing those needs.
And Netlify's deploy, preview and build infrastructure.
Again, like I said, already provides the actionable signals agents need.
When a build fails, an agent can read the logs because we went and updated them,
diagnose the root cause, and submit a fix all without a human in the loop.
And this isn't some future.
This is happening every day and this will happen in your workforces as well.
There will be a demand that comes in and says there's your common path
to turn it into a software factory. Make it go
our agent.
Runners are protected.
We give agents sandbox environments with full platform access.
They deploy, configure, iterate without humans deploy from agents
mean every change gets a unique URL preview URL.
This is where we bring the human back into it.
The human gets to visually look
at the output and continue to iterate, because when you're flowing and vibing,
if you vibe code, you know all it is is about that preview, preview, preview.
And here's a specific example of a redesigned surface.
As I mentioned, our build logs used to be human readable narratives.
Great for scanning, great for DevOps, great for debugging.
Terrible, terrible for agents.
It had no idea what we're talking about.
It wasn't leet speak, it was log speak, which is even worse.
We restructured them into a structured format with machine-readable error codes.
Alongside that, human text and agent can now parse
a build failure, identify missing dependency, and fix it automatically.
But again, here's the thing.
That same structured output made our dashboard clear
for human engineers too, because we took it and really put emphasis
on how an agent would utilize our logs to make decisions.
That also meant that our developers could bug quicker
if the agent didn't know what was going on.
Because I don't know about your.
But I still don't trust agents 100%.
Especially not my Claude bot. It kind of hates me.
Error categorization at a glance.
Failure reasons.
And what we learned again
was this part of the agent experience really did improve the human experience.
It made us quicker to debug any of those problems,
because we were thinking about how an agent would read it to.
But I'm sure most of you all live in the world that I live in.
If only we had greenfield technology and architecture.
That was simple.
This would not be a problem at all.
In fact, you would probably be building
the next 500,000 tech startups because you can do that.
But the problem that most of us face is we're introducing agents
into fragmented systems that have been existing.
Even if you're building net new, I implore you to think
about your agent experience before you start hands on keyboard.
A lot of these systems are collections of APIs, microservices, CI pipelines
that, again, were designed for human operators.
There was an intent that a human would be a part of that loop,
even if stuff was sent to work continuously.
Agents struggled with this.
They can't see across service boundaries.
Every API speaks a different dialect.
Critical workflows live in tribal knowledge and in someone's head.
In a slack thread from 2022, in an undocumented Terraform module,
when agents can't observe the system, they can't act intelligently.
No longer can you rely on tribal knowledge or the person that down the hall on
slack to be like, yo, what did this do? I have no idea.
You're expected
to make it work for your agents because your agent should just work.
This is the fundamental change.
We just can't bolt agents into existing legacy architectures.
The architecture itself must evolve.
The first architectural shift is from APIs to capabilities.
Traditional systems expose rest in points. Post to this.
You'll put to that one.
Get this resource.
An agent looking at a 200 endpoint API surface has to figure out the right
context, the right sequence, the right parameters in the right order.
And I know we're making jokes about context windows.
Believe me, you will run out of time
if you don't specify what agents are supposed to do in your systems.
Agent native systems expose these intent level operations.
Create a site.
Look again.
Plain English deploy repository provision edge compute.
These are capability agents can reason about.
They express what you want to accomplish, not the mechanical steps to get there.
And at Netlify again
we've evolved our API service to support both modes traditional Rest
for existing integrations and capability based interfaces for agent interactions.
This also extended to our CLI.
When you use a CLI, commonly you have a developer that has to hit yes no.
Next parameter that does not work when you have an agent.
We had to go rethink about how our CLI will be utilized.
The second shift is from request response.
Oh man, I'm going to go faster — to event-driven architecture.
Traditional APIs are pull-based.
You send a request, you get a response.
Agents have to poll, guess, and retry. AI-native systems push events. Again,
deploy started PR created agents, subscribe to these events and act.
So if you're still doing stuff asynchronously, you need to think about
updating your systems to event base.
I know we all love Kafka, and so you can use any kind of streaming that you love,
but that's just one way to get there.
This was already how we built the Netlify build system.
Every deploy emits events, and so now the structure, logs
and infrastructure was designed for observable
agents
are the ones observing versus the humans.
The third shift, and probably the most important,
is making architecture legible to agents.
Again, a lot of these distributed systems run on tribal knowledge.
Somebody that knows this service may not know service B. Agents
don't have that knowledge.
This is why we created our system of record called blueprints.
Yes, this is skills, context and recipes.
Think of it as the CLAUDE.md files, AGENTS.md,
the architecture decision records and design
so coding agents understand the system for they make the changes.
The goal isn't better documentation, it's ensuring agents can operate
safely in complex systems.
Putting it all together, we have removed.
We have moved from static tool change to agent orchestrated systems.
This development cycle becomes a continuous human agent loop.
So no longer is it a handoff, it is everybody participating at the same time.
And the human stays in the loop by providing judgment, taste, direction.
But the move, the loop moves at machine speed.
This isn't replacing engineers.
It's amplifying everybody's ability to be a builder.
Now, with all this power, you heard it.
Here comes with serious responsibility, where agents can deploy
code, provision infrastructure and modify production systems.
Trust has to be default and is not optional.
We have three principles we follow at Netlify.
First, sandbox execution.
They can't.
Agents can't escape their sandbox and access resources.
They're not granted.
Second human in the loop by default.
I know you say like you heard me say software factory.
You don't need one.
But guess what?
I still don't trust stuff 100%.
But we want to make the human in the loop the meaningful part of the job.
The agent builds, the human approves, and third audit and roll back.
Every agent action —
every action is logged.
This is where events become so incredibly important
knowing the changes in the system, because today
a lot of code is not being stored in git, which is absolutely bonkers.
But we still have to have a system of record to roll it back.
Trust is built on this transparency.
If you can't explain what the agent did, why would you trust it in production?
The organizational impact is profound.
When we
when agents lower the barrier to building, now the entire company participates.
Everybody's making prototypes.
We're testing hypotheses, coming up with ideas,
supports creating internal tools, custom solutions for customers.
No longer are you bound by the engineering software development lifecycle.
You now have the ability to go let everybody get out of your hair
and just go right and build their own code.
As a DevOps professional,
this has been my dream for over 20 years is build it yourself.
Let me work on the hard problems and now that's what we get to do.
Engineering evolves into implementing from implementing every feature
to really ensuring that the systems have the guardrails.
The architecture is tight and solid.
The skills, recipe and context just work.
This is where AX is critical.
It's a discipline that ensures that democratization happens safely.
Because I don't know about you, I still believe in an open web.
So let me summarize the takeaways
and I want you to take this home first.
I hate to break it to you. We ain't precious no more.
The builder persona has expanded your platforms.
Don't just serve professional developers anymore.
Agents are enabling therapist, teachers,
students, and anybody that has a dream to build and design.
So design for them.
Second, legacy legacy systems must evolve.
APIs need to become capabilities that agents can reason about again,
intent level operations.
Third, safety and trust are foundational.
Sandboxing human and loop reviews. Full audit trails.
These aren't nice to haves.
When agents can deploy to productions, they are have to haves and forth.
This is what you can start shipping well tomorrow.
Go fix your structured errors.
Go create event driven signals and legible architecture.
There's an expert spa I heard.
Go sign up now if you haven't done it before,
go learn how to write your dang skills because your job depends on it.
Would have to say that, but I do.
So our biggest takeaway here is designing for agents
didn't just make our systems better, it made it better for humans.
And that was really the surprise of it all.
This wasn't a trade off for a developer experience or the user experience.
It was a multiplier.
And so why does all this matter?
Because, as Matt says, when anybody can generate
software, code is no longer the scarce, scarce resource.
For decades, the bottleneck has been writing code,
finding engineers, shipping features.
The bottleneck is dissolving.
Now the scarce resource becomes taste.
Know what's worth building, judgment,
knowing when to ship in architecture, designing systems at scale.
And this is where we come full circle.
Full circle.
Ax didn't just help agents
work with our platform, it forced us to clarify our architecture,
our structure, and our signals, in fact, made us all better developers.
So the judgment to build systems agents can work with
that is the engineering skill of the future.
An agent experience ensures
agents amplify human creativity rather than replacing it.
And so this brings us back to Toria.
After hitting the wall of git in a million problems.
She didn't give up.
With an ecosystem designed for agents designed for her,
she bypassed all of those roadblocks.
She was able to drag and drop her intentions into Netlify.
And it just worked.
No git, no CLI, no deployment configurations, no worries.
Trust.
By default, the agent handled all of it.
She called me that day and I remember it.
And I'll censor it since it's a stream.
She called me and she said, girl.
I am a developer.
And I was like, oh man. But she's right.
That's the most incredible part. I didn't build this site.
She did.
Here's her vision.
I hope you all go to the Barbados with us.
Here's her vision. Live for the world to see.
This is AX in action — we designed for agents, and doing so,
we made building possible
for a massage therapist in Barbados who writes intentions and not code.
That's not just agent experience, that's actually human experience.
And that's what agent experience is for.
Thank you for your time.
And if you want to participate, we have some resources available.
Turns out redesigning for everyone is the agent experience.
Experience not designing for agents.
So don't get stuck in the trap.
Remember who you serve and if you want to learn more, you can visit Netlify.
Thanks.
Thank you very much, Dana for a wonderful session.
We have four minutes for questions, so if you have questions,
please do raise your hand and someone will run at you with a mic.
Any questions for Dana at all?
They're blown away.
It's blown away. Yeah.
One question from.
You said
500,000 apps could be built, or we're going to build so much ever.
When do we we're learning these context.
Now, when do we talk about what not to build and how do you stop,
like the environmental impacts, the impact on complexity of code, etc.?
I think that's the challenge that we have right now is
the bitter truth is you're going to be stuck building a whole bunch of stuff
that's going to be obsolete probably in months, not years.
And so finding the right paths and putting intent in the right areas
is what's going to be the keeper.
I mean, hopefully we all continue to think environmentally and conscious
about the world, because building AI
for not anybody on the planet, what's the point?
But there is a bunch of slop right now,
and a bunch of these applications are going to be a drain on our resources.
But this is where development and engineering practices are core to this,
because now anybody in the world can build and literally anybody can.
We have to burden that responsibility on our shoulders to make sure
that we are implementing compaction, that we are thinking about compression,
that we are building the right resources to make the internet continue
to be open and democratized for everybody, but also being environmentally friendly.
And those are the things that these builders won't understand.
So when I talk to people and say, oh, you know, you're getting in development,
I had to be like, well, I don't know if I'd be like a builder.
I would probably focus on the internals and take that background in computer
science and really apply that,
because there's still a lot that we we can do as developers.
But but that that shift is changing for some of these experiences
that we all have. Anybody can do them now.
And so not getting stuck in that trap is is incredibly important.
We have one just to the right.
Oh yeah.
We got a question over here.
Hi. It was a really insightful talk.
Thank you for that.
I wanted to ask about accountability.
So how is your company approaching accountability
where if you're creating useful abstractions and people
building, it doesn't don't understand what's below the abstraction.
Where does accountability sit in that?
Are you planning to, like, flip the accountability and say, we will
give you exposure to what's underneath if you need if you have an IT team?
If not, we will take the accountability.
How are you thinking about that?
I mean, you know, it's it's a it's a push and pull.
I mean, again, it's
like what do I want to build right now that's going to be commoditized.
You know, there used to be a lot of systems
that were super simple, super complex to use that.
Now you just plug and play.
And I think we're in a world where nothing is
really set on, on what will be developed next.
And so again, it's finding the right balance in two parts.
A lot of our users at Netlify come in and want to build websites and applications.
So we are going to put
all the accountability and context in the trust in the system.
So under the hood where you saw on guys talk, that's all Netlify.
We do every bit of that build, deploy, you know, QA, etc.
but in large scale organizations, because Netlify is still built
for developers, we still have this context of a control plane.
We're working on things like policy engines, control panels, really for,
you know, whether it's the CSO or production, R&D,
whoever's doing the guardrails, be able to have that control panel.
But a lot of it, what we're building is often skated, because what we found
is, again, the internet is just a collection of apps and websites.
They're not that complex. I hate to break it to you.
It's usually some JavaScript and maybe a database.
Not a lot of serverless functions in between.
People don't describe building like that anymore.
They say, build me a website that can be shown in Portugal.
That's a serverless function that's doing locality.
They're not going to go in there and write that function.
I'm going to do that for them.
They're just going to come and tell me I want this in Portugal.
And so we are trying to balance where developer
needs to put their attention and where they don't.
And so really utilizing what's important to that system
and more of it is governance policy and identity.
That's what
a lot of large scale enterprises and professional systems care about.
As far as accountability
and more of the hobbyists or solopreneurs, they just want it to work.
I don't care.
We actually don't have any more time for extra questions,
but please do grab Dana in the hallway track.
Once again, thanks very much, Dana.